Ely Samuel Parker Papers 1794-1946 Mss.497.3.P223
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1794-1946; 1.5 linear feet
  - AL to W.H.C. Hosmer, 1845 Oct. 30; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Incomplete letter giving part of the myth of creation.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1845 Nov. 7; Fellows, Joseph, 1782-1873 (Box 1)
    An acknowledgment of Parker's letter of the 4th inst., in which Fellows states the Ogden Co. stands ready to carry out the treaty in good faith and that litigation must result in disappointment to the Indians.
  - ALS to Hasanoanda [i.e., Ely S. Parker], 1845 Nov. 14; Schenandoah [i.e. Morgan, Lewis Henry] (Box 1)
    Letter, addressed to Hasanoanda and signed Schenandoah, recommending that an official statement of the Indian view of the treaty be made public.
  - AMs, "If the Savage Life...", 1845 Nov. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    An address delivered at Cayuga Academy on happiness to the savage and the delights of Indian life.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1845 Dec. 8; Green, L. S. (Box 1)
    Chatty letter from a former school friend now teaching school.
  - AMs, "Live for something noble", 1845 ?; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Essay, a plea for Christianity.
  - AMs, "Melancholy Decay of the Indians", 1845 ?; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 1)
    Part of an essay.
  - AMs, "Give Place to New Ideas", 1846 Jan. 14; Jeminay, Alexander (Box 2)
    Composition written by a student of Genesee Wyoming Seminary and signed "Wannisheyo."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Jan. 20; Porter, Charles Talbot (Box 2)
    Letter advising that the meeting Parker is to address must be postponed a week.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Mar. 9; Parsons, Sylvester (Box 2)
    Letter from a school friend, urging Parker to join him at Wilson Collegiate Institute next term and to enter Williams College with him in the Fall.
  - Accounts, 1846 Mar. 28; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Expenses incurred attending school at Aurora Oct. 1845 to Mar. 1846.
  - [U.S. Congressional Globe], 1846 Apr. 2 (Box 2)
    Clipping reporting that petitions of Tonawandas re. Treaties of 1838 and 1842 were ordered referred to Committee on Indian Affairs.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Apr. 5; Brown, William Linn (Box 2)
    Letter reporting on progress in Senate of Tonawanda petition re. Treaties.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Apr. 12; Flagler, Henry M. (Box 2)
    Letter from a school friend describing a prank at Yates.
  - ALS to Tonawanda Chiefs, 1846 Apr. 18; Wright, Silas (Box 2)
    Parker's copy of a letter from the Governor of New York, stating he has no power to prevent the execution of the Treaties which were made with the authorities of the U.S. and advising the Indians against the use of force.
  - LS to Tonawanda Indians, 1846 Apr. 22; Brown, William Linn (Box 2)
    Letter signed by W.L. Brown enumerating facts, documents, testimony, etc. that will be needed for "the full and final hearing" before the Senate in regard to Treaties.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 May 7; Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864 (Box 2)
    Letter answering Parker's questions of the 2nd inst., stating that in his opinion the Cattaraugus and Alleghany reservations "are insufficient in extent to accommodate permanently the entire Seneca population," and that in obtaining the vote of an Indian council "in former times the majority principle was not known... the objection of a single chief operated... as a veto."
  - Diary (excerpt), 1846 May 18 to 21; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Single page of a diary, commenting on interviews with Commissioner Medill and on Mr. Fellows' efforts to get an appraisal made of the Tonawandas' improvements.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 May 19; Shanks, Isaac, Doctor, Isaac, and Parker, Nicholson (Box 2)
    Letter stating that as a result of following Parker's advice to retaliate against White settlers they have been arrested for trespassing and will be defended in Batavia by Martindale and Verplink [!].
  - AL to "Friend Davis", 1846 May 27; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Incomplete letter describing the Washington scene, with comments on the National Fair, an assembly of Odd Fellows, and James K. Polk, "the curious, unknown critter."
  - ALS to Caroline G. Parker, 1846 May 28; Morgan, Lewis Henry, 1818-1881 (Box 2)
    Original of slightly mutilated letter, with photostat of same, inquiring about her progress at school in Aurora and asking her to write and send him Indian place names with definitions.
  - AL to Senator A. H. Sevier, 1846 June 2; Brown, William Linn (Box 2)
    Letter written from Havana stating that "the Charleston packet has just arrived without the communications anticipated" and enclosing a formal request for an extension of time to July 1st for his appearance before the Committee on Indian Affairs for the hearing of the Tonawanda Indians' case.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 June 7; Warren, R. B. (Box 2)
    Friendly letter containing comments on whether Warren is elected to the Grand Confederacy of the Iroquois, the suits for trespassing, possible delaying tactics for removal of the Indians, Governor Wright's participation in the matter, etc.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1846 June 8; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    A letter from Washington to his brother in Enterprise, Mo., reporting on developments in the Tonawandas' struggle to keep their land, concluding with a brief reference to the death of Solomon, their youngest brother, and to Ely's hope "to visit the West this summer and if I could get a profitable berth anywhere, I don't know but I would stay."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 June 11; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 2)
    An acknowledgment of Ely's letter of May 23. Nic attended a council at which not more than 10 Indians expressed a desire to go West, Geo. W. Clinton, Quaker representatives, and Judge Love were present. Latter believes Ogden Co. would rather pay full value of improvements ($30,000) than take the matter to court, warns Indians against accepting Company offers without consulting competent lawyers like Verplanck and Martindale, and suggests ways to evict Woldren and other intruders.
  - Memorandum, 1846 June 12?; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 2)
    Memo on conferences at Batavia and Albany with attorney Martindale, State Senator Clark, and the Governor, on course of legal action for removing White settlers.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1846 June 14; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    A reply, discussing Judge Love's advice as reported in his brother's letter of June 11. Ely is weary of waiting for Brown's return and finds Washington dull and expensive.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1846 June 21; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Ely acknowledges his brother's letter of the 15th, expressing regret at the lack of unity among the Tonawandas, which he ascribes to Stephen's envy, tracing an analogy between himself and Stephen and David and Goliath. Ely encourages Nic to go away to earn money to continue his studies, even though this means deserting the Indians, stating "I have positively been made poor in serving them so faithfully... I do think they have abused our family enough.
  - ALS to [Caroline Parker?], 1846 June 22; Hurd, I. S. (Box 2)
    Letter from an older correspondent, urging her to continue making an effort in her studies. He prays she and Sarah will be faithful to the word of God. No word from Ely since his return to Washington, but he is not worried about payment of note. Asks to be remembered to mutual friends in Aurora.
  - ANS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 June 30; Martindale, J. H. (Box 2)
    Brief letter transmitting draft for $70.00.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 July 6; Warren, R. B. (Box 2)
    Acknowledges Ely's letter of June 25. Remarks on death of Mr. Herrick and Gen. Scott who "next to Henry Clay is my choice for President in 1848." Mary F. Robinson was married June 30 to S. L. Love and Mr. Barrows married Love's sister July 1. Received letter from Governor Wright saying state government has no authority in Ogden matter. Indians have sued Waldron for rent of saw mill.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1846 July 15; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Ely believes a commission will be appointed to adjudicate Ogden matter. Mr. Brown returned July 14 and they have had a talk with the Commissioner of Indian Affairs. Osborn has been replaced by Angel as New York sub-agent, to which Quaker Thomas "a d---n rascal who interferes too much in Seneca affairs" objected. Gossip about his manner of living, contestants in a forthcoming foot race, etc., etc.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 July 15; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 2)
    Letter signed by 15 chiefs urging speedy action in getting Tonawanda case before the Senate, authorizing Ely to work alone toward this end in the event of Mr. Brown's continued absence, and stating that following Waldron's eviction, a Deputy Sheriff, frightening the Indians with a pistol, took the sawmill out of their possession before three hours had expired.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 July 22; Warren, R. B. (Box 2)
    Letter acknowledging Ely's of the 17th. Warren discusses a pending tariff bill; states Asa Cutler has been to see Mr. Fellows, who says every effort will soon be made to move the Indians west; and accuses Governor Wright, "a snake in the grass," of being on the side of the Ogden Co.'s interests.
  - ALS to George Jamerson and Thompson S. Harris., 1846 July 24; Dole, Benjamin. (Box 2)
    Letter to two Seneca chiefs, acknowledging theirs of June 29 from Fort Scott, Mo. States Mr. Fellows is considering Schedule D and that the writer realizes their need for funds. Osborn has been replaced as sub-agent by Angel of Ellicottville, who will favor emigration. Urges them to write a favorable report of the country, so as to encourage others to follow. Sorry to learn of their complaints against Dr. Hogeboom who has returned and reported they are in good spirits.
  - National Intelligencer, 1846 Aug. 6 (Box 2)
    Clipping headed "Reports from Committees with statements by Mr. Sevier and Mr. Jarnagin, members of the Committee on Indian Affairs, outlining the Committee's reasons for postponing a decision on the Tonawanda case until the next meeting of Congress.
  - ALS to Martha(?), 1846 Aug. 7; Parker, Ely S.(?) (Box 2)
    First page of an unfinished reply to Martha's letter of July 22, mentioning his disappointment that the Tonawandas' case has been "referred to the action of the next Congress."
  - ALS to W. P. Angel, 1846 Aug. 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Letter to the New York Indian sub-agent, giving the number of Tonawandas entitled to annuity money and goods as stipulated by treaties and contracts.
  - Indian Census form, 1846 Aug.?; U.S. Office of Indian Affairs (Box 2)
    Printed form for use in taking Indian census.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Oct. 6; Tryon, I. S. (Box 2)
    A request for Seneca equivalants of some English words to be used in selecting a name for a textile factory.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1846 Oct. 11; Angel, W. P. (Box 2)
    The Indian agent acknowledges Parker's letter of September 29 and regrets that some Tonawandas have refused to supply information Parker has been authorized to obtain. Angel instructs Parker to assure the chiefs the "proposed census has no concealed or hostile object" and applies to all Indians within the U.S. and its territories. Hopes to visit reservation soon to present in Council matter of importance concerning annuity money wasted by a preceding agent.
  - ALS to George Jamerson and Thompson S. Harris, 1846 Oct. 11; Dole, Benjamin. (Box 2)
    Acknowledges letter of Sept. 5, stating Mr. Fellows has not yet paid their claim, but if matter is not settled soon he "will endeavor to force collection by a course of law." Regrets reports of sickness, but writes "it is a calamity which has been common to the whole country." There has been no appropriation from Congress to pay schedules. Asks them to let him know if they are receiving provisions from the government as stipulated and to send him names of the deceased.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1846 Oct. 13; Parker, William H. (Box 2)
    Somewhat mutilated letter, giving news of the family and expressing hope his son will come East for a visit. Father believes mortality rate among those who went West is sufficient grounds for doing all he can "to save our lands from grasp of iniquitous Ogden Land Co." He has renounced liquor and adopted Christianity.
  - ALS to William Medill, 1846 Oct. 15; Avery, Benjamin F. (Box 2)
    Typed copies of letter enclosing receipts amounting to $46.00 [?], covering E.S. Parker's expenses incurred on business in Washington on behalf of the Seneca Indians and of a petition from the Chiefs requesting that "the said Ely S. Parker may not lose the allowance he receives to assist him in his education" which was interrupted in March 1846 because they "have had and still continue to have great use for his services."
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1846 Oct. 27; Parker, Levi (Box 2)
    Acknowledges his brother's letter received Oct. 2. Levi's dog is dead. Family is all together and well, and even though they lose their lands they will not go West to such "mean country."
  - LS Cy to Silas Wright, 1846 Nov. 9; Tonawanda Chiefs (Box 2)
    Photostat of letter requesting the Governor of New York "to enter proper complaints...under the Law of 1821" against White intruders. Indians have been informed by Wm. Brown of Philadelphia, who has had an interview with Wright, that State will protect them.
  - Mental Elevator, No. 13, 1846 Dec. 24 (Box 2)
    One 8 p. issue, published in the main in Seneca, but partly in English, by the Mission Press, Cattaraugus Reservation, N.Y. Contains census returns for 1845-46 and "Results of Emigration." Latter article lists name of Thompson S. Harris and of other deceased members of the party who left for the West in May 1846.
  - Diary, 1847 Jan. 1-13; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Twenty-two pages of a diary with comments on New Year's Day calls on President Polk, Dolly Madison and others; paintings of Indians in the Capitol; Sunday sermons on Christianity; a fire at Jackson's Hall during a celebration in honor of Jackson's victory at New Orleans; funeral of Senator Pennybacker; meetings with sympathetic senators; Ely's efforts on behalf of the Tonawanda Indians' land case, etc.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Jan. 11; Parker, Levi (Box 2)
    Levi has received a letter from Benjamin Williams informing him that two thirds of the Indians who went West in the Spring have died.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Jan. 15; Parker, Nicholson H. (Box 2)
    Letter advising that Cattaraugus Seneca have refused to sign a petition drafted by Tonawanda Senecas and enclosing statement of losses in money and goods for Ely's corrections.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Jan. 25; Blacksmith, John and Johnson, James (Box 2)
    Decision has been reached in Council to send Chiefs Blacksmith and Shanks to be with Ely in Washington, so that "the blame might not rest upon him so strongly if we should happen to loose our lands." The full authority vested earlier in Ely is not to be affected by this decision.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1847 Feb. 2; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Brief letter advising brother not to include languages in his studies at Alexander.
  - ALS to Nicholson H. Parker, 1847 Feb. 17; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Letter reporting briefly on the progress of the Tonawanda case before Congress.
  - Senate Document 156., 1847 Feb. 19; U.S. Congress, 29th, 2nd Session (Box 2)
    The Committee on Indian Affairs has refused to exempt the Tonawanda Band from the provisions of the Treaty, on the grounds that it was ratified May 20, 1842 by the Senate, in spite of the same evidence of fraud, etc.
  - ALS to Nicholson Parker, 1847 Feb. 28; Parker, Caroline (Box 2)
    Spencer has returned home and he and other members of the family are not well. Caroline has had another letter from L.H. Morgan and fears he is disappointed in her knowledge of Indian grammar.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1847 Mar. 18; Harlin, D. M. (Box 2)
    A letter from Enterprise, Mo., stating that Isaac Love, who has been substituting as miller for Cone during the latter's absence, is to be superseded in April by a Mr. Britten who has apparently bribed the Chiefs to consent to his appointment.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Mar. 20; Porter, Charles Talbot (Box 2)
    Acknowledges letter from Ely, stating he and Goodwin have no money to send him. Suggests that Ely call on Mr. Yates and A.B. Street in Albany, who "are well off." Street is writing a poem on the Iroquois and Porter a history of the Ogden matter, and both authors will need Ely's help.
  - ALS to William Parker, 1847 Mar. 22; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    A letter to his parents requesting that they send him $20.00 at once as a loan. Ely has stopped for a few days in Albany to see the new Governor.
  - [Albany Newspaper], 1847 Mar. 29 (Box 2)
    Clipping mentioning Indian lobby with names of delegates, the adoption by the Seneca of Lewis Henry Morgan, C. T. Porter and Thomas Darling, and other news items.
  - [Rochester Daily Democrat?], 1847 Apr.1(?); Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Two clippings dealing with Bills introduced before the State Legislature, one appropriating $2,000 to provide for the return East of the surviving emigrants, and another allowing $300 for school purposes.
  - AMs Cy extract, 1847 May 28; Wilson, Peter (Box 2)
    Abstract by Ely S. Parker of an address by an educated Indian delivered before the New York Historical Society, which contrasts the part played by the Iroquois in the development and history of the Empire State with their present unhappy position.
  - ALS to Spencer H. Cone, 1847 May 29; Harlin, D. M. (Box 2)
    Letter enclosing a petition to the Secretary of War, signed by 25 customers of the mill, setting forth Cone's "claims as Seneca miller." Letter states the present incumbent, John Britton, is incompetent.
  - ALS to William L. Marcy, Secretary of War, 1847 June 7; Tonawanda Indians (Box 2)
    Document with 2-1/2 pages of signatures in double columns, denying the existence of an "emigrationist party" and stating the Band is unanimous in preferring their lands to the Ogden Land Co.'s money for improvements.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 June 10; Porter, Charles Talbot (Box 2)
    Letter requesting Ely to submit promptly Indian names, etc. for the 4 degrees of the "Hodenosonnee" secret society so that plans can be completed for an organization meeting in August.
  - AMs, "New Initiation of the Wolf Tribe of the Cayuga Nation...", 1847 [June?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    "...one of the Confederate Nations of the Grand Confederacy of Iroquois." [i.e. Morgan's secret society.]
  - AL to [Commissioner of Indian Affairs], 1847 July 5; Cone, Spencer H. (Box 2)
    First page only of a letter written from Pembroke, N.Y., contesting his replacement as Miller within the Nosho sub-agency, by John Britton, a white man, and explaining that his absence since December was due to the appointment of himself and George Jemison as delegates to plead the cause in Washington of the emigrants and that their traveling funds gave out when they reached Buffalo.
  - Accounts, 1847 Oct. 30; Tonawanda Band of Seneca Indians (Box 2)
    Brief statement, signed by 15 chiefs, of expenditures totaling $5,079.31, spent in defense of national rights from 1838 to 1847.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Nov. 12; Moseley, W. A. (Box 2)
    Letter written from Buffalo, advising he can exert no further influence with regard to Ely's application for admission to Harvard University, and suggesting that he approach some Quaker friends.
  - ALS to [Caroline Parker?], 1847 Nov. 14; Hurd, I. S. (Box 2)
    A pious letter on the joy of living close to God, with a few brief references to mutual friends.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Nov. 15; Street, Alfred B. (Box 2)
    Letter asking advice on the use of Indian words in a poem he is writing, and promising that he and Mr. Yates will do their best to find a position in Albany for Ely.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1847 Dec. 16; Angel, W. P. (Box 2)
    Letter from the Indian agent concerning arrangements for the payment of $400 to the Tonawanda chiefs and requesting a statement signed by them concerning "their wishes and determination in regard to the census."
  - AMsS to Caroline [Parker?], 1847(?); Warren, N. S. (Box 2)
    A poem about faithful friends, inscribed at Tonawanda Mission.
  - DS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Jan. 5; Tonawanda Band of Seneca Indians (Box 2)
    Original and typed copy of Power-of-Attorney, authorizing Ely S. Parker and Isaac Shanks to act on behalf of the Band. Document bears names and marks of 2 witnesses, 9 warriors and 16 chiefs.
  - Diary, "Notes on the Road", 1848 Jan. 8 to 18; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    An 8 page diary entitled "Notes on the Road," covering incidents and personalities encountered in New York, Philadelphia and Washington.
  - ALS to Tonawanda Chiefs, 1848 Jan. 15; Shanks, Isaac and Parker, Ely S. (Box 2)
    The delegates report they gave $50 to Brown in Philadelphia as instructed, and that they have learned the Tonawandas' case died with the unfinished business of the last Congress. Shanks is ill.
  - ALS to William Medill, 1848 Jan. 21; Parker, Ely S. and Shanks, Isaac (Box 2)
    A summary statement by the delegates to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs of the difficulties between the Tonawanda Senecas and the Ogden Land Co. They will not accept any part of the payment for the improvements on their land, nor permit an appraisement of these improvements, as they were dissenting parties to the treaties which so provided.
  - ALS to the Treasurer of the State of North Carolina, 1848 Feb. 1; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    A request for information about funds held in trust, resulting from the sale of land formerly owned by the Tuscarora Indians.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Feb. 11; Hinton, C. L. (Box 2)
    A reply from the Treasurer of North Carolina, stating that the sale of Tuscarora lands yielded $3,220.71, which amount was paid to their agent in 1832.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Feb. 20; Angel, W. P. (Box 2)
    The Indian agent advises he believes the district attorney, under the Statute of 1813, can compel the county judge to issue warrants for removal of White intruders. Angel offers to pay Ely's board in exchange for services in Ellicottville. Would like to have Tonawanda census as soon as "your brother... gets it completed."
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Feb. 27; Van Horn, Burt (Box 2)
    An invitation to visit a friend, with expenses paid, so that they can practice "a dialogue" for an "exhibition" in Newfane in March.
  - ALS to Ely S. Parker, 1848 Mar. 31; Cone, Spencer H. (Box 2)
    Instructions to Parker in Ellicottville to be at Cattaraugus April 5 to witness the signatures of Tonawanda chiefs on annuity receipts.
  - "Indians on Religion", 1848 [May 1?]; [Parker, Ely S.? (Box 2)
    Newspaper clipping, entitled "Indians on Religion," signed Seneca.
  - 1848 [May] 23, [Wright, Asher?] (Box 2)
    Eight lines written in Seneca, in pencil, on a scrap of paper, without English translation.
  - ALS to [Henry Rowe Schoolcraft?], 1848 May?; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    An unfinished reply to a request for a "succint account of the Tonawandas," and "the expulsion of the Eries."
  - Notes, 1848 [May?]; Parker, Ely Samuel, 1828-1895 (Box 2)
    Notes on the following topics: History of the Iroquois Confederacy or Six Nations; International Rank and Relations; Geography; Astronomy; and Medicine.